Hi!
Do you know how fast electrons travel in a wire,
...considering electricity travels
close to the speed of light?
When you make a phone call,
...your voice reaches the other side
of the planet almost instantly.
With a click of a button,
...the Nigerian prince has your
credit card information in a snap.
Well, let's calculate.
I cut 1 centimetre (1 cm) length of this
...22 gauge wire.
I calculated that in this tiny piece of wire,
...there is roughly around
...280 million trillion copper atoms,
...assuming that it's pure copper.
You can check my calculation sheet in the description.
Every copper atom
...has one loosely held electron
...that can be pushed around to create electric current.
...and the charge of one electron is around:
Very small.
Charge of one electron times their number
...means there is around 44 coulombs
(44 C) worth of electron charge in the wire,
...ready to move and create electric current,
...which are held by the same number of protons,
...and the wire is electrically neutral.
Now imagine we want to run
...1 amp (1A) of current through this tiny piece of wire.
1 amp (1 A) is a lot of current.
It can kill you instantly,
...and can run, like,
...a hundred Hamaguchi games
...to entertain a bunch of losers.
No offense.
Current (in ampere)
...is the amount of charge (in coulomb)
passing per second.
So, 1 amp (1 A) of current
...is 1 coulomb (1 C) of charge (q)
passing per second.
Considering we have 44 coulombs (44 C) of charge
...in that 1-centimetre (1 cm) piece of wire,
...the speed of charges would be
...centimetre per second (cm/s),
...or only
...millimetres per second!
It's so slow!
It's a speed like this:
ʏᴇᴘ, ɪᴛ ɪꜱ ꜱʟᴏᴡ
ᴏᴋᴀʏ, ᴡᴇ ɢᴇᴛ ɪᴛ
ᴜʜ, ᴍᴇʜᴅɪ
ʏᴏᴜ ᴄᴀɴ ꜱᴛᴏᴘ ɴᴏᴡ
ᴍᴏᴍ ɪ'ᴍ ꜱᴄᴀʀᴇᴅ
∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀∀
Now life makes much more sense!
I was always wondering, in a battery
...how all these electrolyte ions and chemicals
...stuck in a boogery goo
...can carry electric current.
They can't mechanically move fast,
...but now I know they don't need to move fast
...to carry massive amount of current.
Then how does electricity move
close to the speed of light?
It's not the electrons that move that fast,
...it's the wave between them.
For example, if I hit this piece of stick with a hammer
...to hit that glass,
The shock waves will
...travel at a speed of-
[glass clatters]
[REDACTED]
The shock wave
...moves at a speed of wave in a stick
...and gets to the other side almost instantly,
...while the particles themselves
only move a little bit forward.
Similarly, if you shove one electron into a wire,
...the electrons repel each other,
...and the electric wave travels
close to the speed of light.
...and one electron will drop out of
the other side almost instantly.
But let's see what happens if we
change the thickness of the wire.
If a wire is very thin,
...it is still tons thicker than your
[REDACTED]
[laughs]
Sorry.
Anyway, in a thinner wire
...we have less available charges to move,
...so to create 1 amp (1 A),
...the 1 coulomb (1 C) would have to move faster.
Because the same amount of charge
that could pass a spot in 1 second
...is spread out
...over a thinner wire
...but still has to pass in 1 second.
Imagine these two magnets
...or two copper atoms
...stuck in the springy crystal
...and this magnet is an electron passing through.
The passing electron
...has to move through the electric fields of the atoms
...and it shakes them too.
There needs to be some energy per charge or voltage
...to force the electron through the fields of the atoms.
And if you want to move faster,
...you need even more voltage
...and the atoms vibrate even more.
What is this vibration of atoms?
It's what we feel as temperature.
Atoms vibrating is heat.
The more they vibrate, the hotter they are.
The faster the electrons pass through them,
...the more vibrations they create
...and the hotter the wire gets.
[pants]
Is that animated enough?
That's why running the same
current through a thinner wire
...creates more heat.
We need more energy to move electrons faster
...through those pesky electric fields of the atoms,
...so we need a higher voltage.
Different atoms hold their electrons with different force.
For example, in iron,
...we need a higher energy to
[straining] ...move the electrons!
[hits table] Ow!
Hss
Ow!
We need a higher energy
...to move the electrons through a stronger field,
...and the motion of electrons
creates more vibration and heat.
It is as if the conductive material
...shows resistance against the motion of charges.
[ ｒ ｅ ａ ｌ ｉ ｓ ａ ｔ ｉ ｏ ｎ ｓ ｅ ｔ ｓ ｉ ｎ ]
And that's what resistance is.
All these pesky electric fields
...not letting electrons to move through freely,
...and wasting energy in the form of heat.
And so the resistance of a conductor was defined by
...[Ohm] as the amount of
voltage or energy per charge
...required to create a certain amount
of current through the conductor,
...or voltage divided by amp.
And that's the Ohm's Law,
...and ohm (Ω) is the unit of resistance
...which is also shown by Omega (Ω).
We can also show it as
...voltage (V) equals to
...resistance (R) times current (I).
So, if we want more current for the same resistance,
...we need to increase the voltage.
Any component made to resist
...is called a:
...and is shown with this symbol,
...I guess because
...the charge would have a hard time
...flowing through these wiggly lines.
The actual resistors could be made as
...through-hole components like this one,
...which means that these pins
...have to go through a board.
And the color stripes indicate the resistance.
Or, they can be made as these
...tiny surface-mount components
...that solder right onto the surface of the board.
Or other types like panel mounts.
I know how to read these colour bands,
...and I suggest you search the web and learn it too.
It would help you find a through-hole
resistor easier through a pile.
Doesn't quite help you with the
surface-mount ones, though,
...but you can always get a meter
...and measure the value and make sure.
But, there is an engineering way
...they typically use to show the values,
...which also applies to capacitors
and inductors and such.
If you see a few digits like:
...the last digit is the number of zeroes
...that would go in front of the first digits
...to make a complete number.
For example, if you see:
...it means that there are
...3 zeroes in front of 110
...to get 110,000.
In case of resistors,
...this is 110 kiloohm (kΩ).
In case of surface-mount components,
...if there's room,
...they just print this number directly on the package.
But in case of through-hole components,
...they just color-code these numbers.
For example, these would be
...brown, brown, black, orange.
The resistance is calculated by this formula.
Oh, right.
You find the way I say 'formula' funny, huh?
How do you say it?
Formula.
Forbula.
[REDACTED], it's:
So, the resistance is equal to some constant
(which is called the:)
(and depends on the type of material,)
(like iron, aluminium, copper or whatever)
...times the length of the wire,
...divided by the area of cross-section of wire.
It is simple.
For a specific material,
...the longer the length of the wire is,
...the more electric fields the charges
would have to go through,
...which makes it harder, and so higher resistance.
And also, the thinner the wire is,
...like I said before, for the same current,
...the charges would have to go faster,
...which means it's harder,
...and again, more resistance.
It's like the flow of water.
Right now, I have a certain pressure
and flow from this hose.
If I make its output thinner,
...the water would have to flow faster
...under the same pressure, which is harder to.
And if I add some length of hose to it,
The flow is even slower,
...as the water has to overcome
the friction against the pipe.
The cup at the center seems to be filling faster,
...but it's not.
The high-speed jet is pushing the water up and out.
For example, I have a 10-ohm (10 Ω) resistor,
...and if I put 10 volts (10 V) across it,
...there will be 1 amp (1 A) through it.
Aw, [REDACTED].
It's burning now.
Which brings us to the subject of power.
Too much power through a resistor
...and it will burn like you saw.
Every component has a specific
continuous power rating.
For example, the one burnt was quarter watt,
...and this one can handle 50 watts (50 W).
But every component can handle
more power than its rating
...for a short period of time.
See, here I have a new 10-ohm (10 Ω) resistor,
...and if I apply 10 volts (10 V) across it momentarily,
...it will remain unharmed.
And that's how I survived the incident.
[flashbacks to Jacob's Ladder video]
[electricity crackles]
Ah, [REDACTED]!
A bit longer,
...and I would have been cooked like this resistor.
Be careful around electronics, kids.
We know that power
...is the amount of energy spent in a given time.
...which is also equal to
...energy (W) divided by charge (q),
...times charge (q) divided by time (t).
And if we look carefully,
...this is just voltage times current!
So we know power (P) is equal to
voltage (V) times current (I).
And from Ohm's Law, we have
...voltage (V) is equal to resistance (R) times current (I).
So we can calculate power (P) to be equal to
...voltage (V) squared (²) divided by resistance (R),
...or resistance (R) times current (I) squared (²).
There's a whole bunch of other stuff
to talk about around resistors,
...but for now, squeeze this information into your heads
...and we'll talk about them later.
And I will probably make an
unlisted problem-solving video
...around what we just talked about,
...so it sticks into your tiny brains better,
...and leave the link in the description below.
Receeeess!
[random noises]
Oh, and I know that this 101 series
...are more boring than my normal videos,
...but I think they serve a good purpose.
I really appreciate your likes
...and the support of my channel at:
You're helping me power through making these videos
...and helping with the school giveaways,
...making everyone smarter.
And in return,
...patrons are always included in any draw,
...and also, there're some
...special other perks!
Thank you.
[ᴛʀᴀᴅɪᴛɪᴏɴᴀʟ ᴜɴɪʙʀᴏᴡ ᴅᴀɴᴄᴇ ᴏᴜᴛʀᴏ]
Subtitles/captions by Jonathan Lee (Pentameron)
youtube.com/c/PentameronSV